<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"docbook/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
	<title>q5go</title>

	<copyright>
	  <year>2011-2019</year>
	  <holder>Bernd Schmidt</holder>
	</copyright>
	<copyright>
	  <year>2001-2003</year>
	  <holder>Peter Strempel, Johannes Mesa, Emmanuel Beranger, Marin Ferecatu</holder>
	</copyright>
  </bookinfo>

<!-- Preface -->
  <preface>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>q5go is a Go client and
	<link linkend="sgf">SGF</link>

	editor written with the Qt library, available for Linux,
	Windows and Mac OS X.</para>

	<para>Go is an ancient boardgame, very common in Japan, China
	and Korea.</para>

	<para>q5go can support translations. Check in the preferences
	dialog if your language is available. If not, you might
	consider translating q5go to your language. Read more about
	<link linkend="language">translations</link>

	in the preferences chapter.</para>

	<para>This manual describes the basic usage of q5go.</para>

	<note>
	  <para>This manual was written against an older version of
	  the program and is neither finished nor up-to-date.</para>
	</note>
  </preface>

<!-- Chapter: File formats -->
  <chapter>
	<title>File formats</title>

<!-- Section: SGF -->
	<section>
	  <title>SGF</title>

	  <anchor id="sgf" />

	  <para>SGF (Smart Game Format) files are a simple and
	  effective way to store records of two-player board games.
	  File information is saved as plain text, which makes the
	  files very small and easy to handle or store. Game
	  information is stored in a tree-based format - in other
	  words, there is one main linear sequence of moves, with any
	  alternatives that have been entered into the record
	  branching away from that main sequence. These branches may
	  have their own branches and so on.</para>

	  <para>Because an SGF can contain much information -
	  including but not limited to board setup, markings,
	  variations, and extensive comments - programs such as q5go
	  have been created. q5go provides a powerful, easy-to-use
	  interface for creating, editing and viewing SGF
	  files.</para>

	  <para>Loading and saving SGF files supports
	  <link linkend="encoding">text encoding</link>

	  for asian languages.</para>
	</section>
  </chapter>

<!-- Chapter: q5go, the Program -->
  <chapter>
	<title>q5go, the Program</title>

<!-- Section Launching -->
	<section>
	  <title>Launching</title>

	  <para>You may simple use a desktop icon or command line
	  input to launch the program. The command line syntax
	  is</para>

	  <para>
	  <userinput>q5go</userinput>

	  [options] [
	  <filename>file</filename>

	  ]</para>

	  <table frame="all">
		<title>Launch parameters</title>

		<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
		  <thead>
			<row>
			  <entry>option</entry>

			  <entry>meaning</entry>
			</row>
		  </thead>

		  <tbody>
			<row>
			  <entry>
				<userinput>-sgf</userinput>
			  </entry>

			  <entry>make new sgf file (or simple open a board to
			  play)</entry>
			</row>

			<row>
			  <entry>
				<userinput>-sgf19</userinput>
			  </entry>

			  <entry>same but don't ask and open 19x19
			  board</entry>
			</row>

			<row>
			  <entry>
				<userinput>-debug</userinput>
			  </entry>

			  <entry>open debug window and show status
			  messages</entry>
			</row>

			<row>
			  <entry>
				<userinput>-desktop</userinput>
			  </entry>

			  <entry>use standard options from desktop</entry>
			</row>

			<row>
			  <entry>
				<filename>file</filename>
			  </entry>

			  <entry>open file (type
			  <link linkend="sgf">SGF</link>

			  )</entry>
			</row>
		  </tbody>
		</tgroup>
	  </table>
	</section>

<!-- Section Structure -->
	<section>
	  <title>Structure</title>

	  <para>q5go has two main windows, one is the client window
	  the other is the board window. Further, there is the debug window, too, but you may not need
	  it.</para>

	  <section>
		<title>Client Window</title>

		<anchor id="client" />

		<para>While handling the connection to internet,
		negotiating your match requests or looking for games to
		observe this is your main window. This window appears on
		starting the q5go program without any of the options
		<userinput>-sgf</userinput>

		,
		<userinput>-sgf19</userinput>

		or
		<filename>filename</filename>

		.</para>

		<para>The client window consists of a players list in the
		upper left, a games list in the upper right, talk windows
		in the lower left, a restricted message window in the
		lower right.</para>

		<para>Further, there is a single edit line, further
		referred as command line, on the lower edge and a bar on
		the right edge containing the hostlist combo box on the
		top.</para>

		<para>Type
		<userinput>#</userinput>

		at the command line to get a list of internal
		commands.</para>

		<note>
		  <para>Starting any text with
		  <userinput>#</userinput>

		  at the command line will parsed as internal command.
		  Nothing is sent to host! E.g.
		  <userinput>#+dbgwin</userinput>

		  as internal command.</para>
		</note>
	  </section>

	  <section>
		<title>Board Window</title>

		<para>The Go board is the most important part of the
		program. It is embedded in the board window. Further the
		board window contains clocks displaying the remaining
		times for each player, edit tools and two comment edit
		windows, a single line field to kibitz online games and a
		multi line field for receiving comments during online
		games or commenting games offline.</para>

		<para>For fast startup, the command line option
		<userinput>-sgf19</userinput>

		,
		<userinput>-sgf</userinput>

		brings up a local (offline) board to edit a game. If
		using
		<filename>filename</filename>

		then the file with name
		<filename>filename</filename>

		is loaded immediately. In any case, the main window will
		not be shown.</para>

		<note>
		  <para>Starting any text with
		  <userinput>#</userinput>

		  at the single edit line will be sent to client window
		  and parsed as a command (without
		  <userinput>#</userinput>

		  ). It is sent to host! Thus, starting with
		  <userinput>##</userinput>

		  will result in a internal command for the client
		  window. E.g.
		  <userinput>#stats</userinput>

		  as host command or
		  <userinput>##+dbgwin</userinput>

		  as internal command.</para>
		</note>
	  </section>

	  <section>
		<title>Debug Window</title>

		<para>For debugging purposes, the debug window can be
		shown with the
		<userinput>-debug</userinput>

		startup option. However, this will set q5go in a debug
		mode, too, which means the program will run
		slower.</para>

		<para>The debug window is always present but it's maybe
		hidden. Thus, the debug window a log viewer for q5go.
		Setting q5go to debug mode means logging more events,
		especially logging all host responses but some internal
		messages, too.</para>

		<para>Therefore, only opening the debug window doesn't
		slow down the q5go program.</para>

		<para>In order to show the debug window there are other
		options:</para>

		<table frame="all">
		  <title>Debug parameters</title>

		  <tgroup cols="4" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
			<thead>
			  <row>
				<entry>command</entry>

				<entry>where to enter</entry>

				<entry>set mode</entry>

				<entry>debug window</entry>
			  </row>
			</thead>

			<tbody>
			  <row>
				<entry>
				  <userinput>-debug</userinput>
				</entry>

				<entry>when launching q5go</entry>

				<entry>DEBUG</entry>

				<entry>show</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>
				  <userinput>#+dbg</userinput>
				</entry>

				<entry>command line</entry>

				<entry>DEBUG</entry>

				<entry>show</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>
				  <userinput>#+dbgwin</userinput>
				</entry>

				<entry>command line</entry>

				<entry>NORMAL</entry>

				<entry>show</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>
				  <userinput>#-dbg</userinput>
				</entry>

				<entry>command line</entry>

				<entry>NORMAL</entry>

				<entry>hide</entry>
			  </row>
			</tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</table>

		<para>command line is the bottom most line of the
		<link linkend="client">client window</link>

		.</para>
	  </section>
	</section>
  </chapter>

<!-- Chapter: Client Window Usage-->
  <chapter>
	<title>Client Window - Usage</title>

	<note>
	  <para>There are a lot of settings saved when q5go is getting
	  closed. Thus, by running several instances of q5go the last
	  closed instance of q5go supersedes the settings.</para>

	  <para>This is different to closing a board window since all
	  board settings are updated simultaneosly and they are saved
	  when q5go quits.</para>
	</note>

<!-- Section Menus -->
	<section>
	  <title>Menus</title>

<!-- Section: File menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>File</title>

		<section>
		  <title>New</title>

		  <para>
		  </para>
		</section>
	  </section>
	</section>

<!-- Section Mouse control -->
	<section>
	  <title>Mouse control</title>

	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>

<!-- Section Keyboard control -->
	<section>
	  <title>Keyboard control</title>

	  <para>
	  </para>
	</section>
  </chapter>

<!-- Chapter: Usage-->
  <chapter>
	<title>Board Window - Usage</title>

<!-- Section Window focus -->
	<section>
	  <title>Window focus</title>

	  <para>Once the comment editor has the window focus, and you
	  want to continue using the
	  <keycap>cursor</keycap>

	  and
	  <keycap>Home</keycap>

	  /
	  <keycap>End</keycap>

	  keys for game navigation, just press
	  <keycap>Escape</keycap>

	  or click onto the board window to return the focus to the
	  board again. With
	  <keycap>Tab</keycap>

	  you can switch from the board to the editor again.</para>

	  <tip>
		<para>If you have a wheelmouse, move the mouse over the
		board and use the wheel for fast navigation.</para>
	  </tip>
	</section>

<!-- Section Menus -->
	<section>
	  <title>Menus</title>

<!-- Section: File menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>File</title>

		<section>
		  <title>New</title>

		  <para>This lets you create a new SGF. You will be
		  prompted for some basic game information (white player,
		  black player, board size, komi, and handicap).</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Open</title>

		  <para>This will open a stored SGF file into the current
		  window. q5go will remember which directory you store
		  your SGFs in and return there next time you perform the
		  Open, Save, or Save As functions during the same
		  session. The file does not have to have an .sgf
		  extension as long as it is in the SGF format (sometimes
		  downloaded files are saved without the
		  extension).</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Save</title>

		  <para>This will save the SGF you are currently editing.
		  If the SGF has not yet been saved to a file, you will
		  be prompted for a filename. If you want to save an
		  existing file under another name or in another
		  location, use the Save As option.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Save As</title>

		  <para>This will let you define which location and name
		  the SGF file will be saved under. Use this to save
		  edited, or alternate copies of SGFs without overwriting
		  the original.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Export ASCII</title>

		  <para>q5go can also export an SGF position into ASCII
		  format. Simply load the position you want to export and
		  then select File - Export ASCII. This opens a window to
		  show you what the exported ASCII file will look like.
		  You can 'Close' window or 'Save' the displayed ASCII
		  position (you will be prompted for a filename). Note
		  that the currently displayed position, not the entire
		  SGF file, is saved in ASCII format. The characters to
		  display the position can be altered in the preferences
		  dialog.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Export image</title>

		  <para>You can export the current board position to an
		  image file. Simply load the position you want to save
		  and select File - Export Image. You will be prompted
		  for a filename to save the image under. Note that this
		  does not produce a screenshot; it produces an image of
		  the board position only. q5go supports common image
		  formats like png, gif, jpeg, bmp. You can the exported
		  file to alter in common graphic suits like Gimp or
		  CorelDraw.</para>

		  <tip>
			<para>If you want to create a graphic of only a
			limited board position, zoom the board and navigate
			to the position you want to display.</para>
		  </tip>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Exit</title>

		  <para>This lets you exit the program.</para>
		</section>
	  </section>

<!-- Section: Edit menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>Edit</title>

		<section>
		  <title>Cut</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Paste</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Paste as brother</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Delete</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>
	  </section>

<!-- Section: Navigation menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>Navigation</title>

		<para>To be written.</para>
	  </section>

<!-- Section: Settings menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>Settings</title>

		<section>
		  <title>Preferences</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>

		<section>
		  <title>Game Info</title>

		  <para>To be written.</para>
		</section>
	  </section>

<!-- Section: View menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>View</title>

		<para>To be written.</para>
	  </section>

<!-- Section: Help menu -->
	  <section>
		<title>Help</title>

		<para>To be written.</para>
	  </section>
	</section>

<!-- Section Preferences -->
	<section>
	  <title>Preferences</title>

	  <para>In the preferences dialog the main features of q5go
	  can be controlled. There are three sections for the
	  Interface, ASCII importing/exporting and SGF
	  loading.</para>

<!-- Section Interface -->
	  <section>
		<title>Interface</title>

		<para>Here the visual settings can be changed. All
		settings are saved and reloaded when q5go starts up the
		next time.</para>

		<para>More detailed information has to be written. Please
		check the tool tips and use the help button in the lower
		left corner to get more help about each button and
		checkbox.</para>

		<anchor id="language" />

		<section>
		  <title>Language</title>

		  <para>You can chose the language in the preferences
		  dialog. If 'System default' is selected, the Unix
		  system locale will be used. To set this, type for
		  example
		  <userinput>export LANG=de_DE</userinput>

		  in your bash, to set your language settings to german.
		  Probably your system has already a locale set, check it
		  by typing
		  <userinput>echo $LANG</userinput>

		  .</para>

		  <para>Actually, I have no clue how the Windows locale
		  is checked. Qt is expecting a string like "de" or
		  "de_DE", but Windows gives the string "C". If you are
		  on Windows, just chose the language manually.</para>

		  <note>
			<para>You have to restart q5go to let the language
			change take effect.</para>
		  </note>
		</section>
	  </section>

<!-- Section ASCII -->
	  <section>
		<title>ASCII</title>

		<para>This tab controls the characters used for importing
		and exporting ASCII boards. This feature can be used for
		posting in textbased groups like rec.games.go. If a
		textfile is imported, the given characters are parsed to
		reconstruct the board position. When a board is exported
		to ASCII, the characters are used to construct the
		textfile.</para>

		<para>When
		<emphasis>Add as brother</emphasis>

		is selected, an imported board position will be added as
		a brother of the current node, if unselected it is added
		as son.</para>

		<para>These settings are currently not saved.</para>
	  </section>

<!-- Section SGF Loading -->
	  <section>
		<title>SGF Loading</title>

		<para>If
		<emphasis>Remember last directory</emphasis>

		is checked, q5go will remember the directory a user loads
		from or saves to and reuse this directory the next time a
		file operation is performed. This can be useful,
		especially on Windows, if one certain directory is used
		for all game files. On Linux, q5go defaults to the users
		home directory, so leaving this option unchecked might be
		more comfortable.</para>

		<para>
		<anchor id="encoding" />

		The
		<emphasis>text encoding</emphasis>

		is useful when dealing with asian languages. When loading
		or saving a SGF file, the given encoding is used. Note,
		changing this setting will take effect the next time a
		game is loaded or saved, it won't affect the currently
		loaded game.</para>

		<para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			  <emphasis>None</emphasis>

			  - Default western latin1 encoding</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			  <para>
			  <emphasis>Japanese</emphasis>

			  - EUC-JP, JIS, Shift-JIS</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			  <para>
			  <emphasis>Chinese</emphasis>

			  - GBK</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
			  <para>
			  <emphasis>Korean</emphasis>

			  - EUC-KR</para>
			</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</para>

		<para>You might need to experiment a bit with these
		settings.</para>

		<para>If you are not using an asian language, leave this
		setting to 'None', this will make loading and saving much
		faster. Especially for Kogo's Joseki dictionary I
		recommand switching this setting to 'None'.</para>

		<para>The encoding settings are automatically saved and
		reloaded the next time q5go starts.</para>

		<para>
		<emphasis>Fast loading</emphasis>

		is an experimental setting. It is not working well. It is
		highly recommanded to unselect this setting.</para>
	  </section>
	</section>

<!-- Section Mouse control -->
	<section>
	  <title>Mouse control</title>

	  <para>q5go offers advanced navigation features by using the
	  mouse only, to provide a comfortable interface to the user.
	  Mouse gestures are implemented as button and wheel
	  gestures.</para>

	  <para>These navigation gestures are an additional feature,
	  they offer basically the same as the toolbar or keyboard
	  control, but are meant to make a convinient way of
	  navigation through a game available.</para>

	  <section>
		<title>Mousebutton navigation</title>

		<para>There are four navigation gestures
		available:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold right, then click left -&gt; Previous
			move</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold left, then click right -&gt; Next
			move</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold middle, then click left -&gt; Start of
			variation</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold middle, then click right -&gt; Go to next
			variation</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<tip>
		  <para>This only applies if the mouse pointer is over
		  the green table part of the window, not if it is over
		  the valid goban, to avoid accidental changes to the
		  game when applying navigation gestures through the
		  mousebuttons.</para>
		</tip>
	  </section>

	  <section>
		<title>Mousewheel navigation</title>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Mousewheel forward -&gt; Previous move</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Mousewheel backward -&gt; Next move</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold right + mousewheel forward -&gt; Previous
			variation</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Hold right + mousewheel backward -&gt; Next
			variation</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<tip>
		  <para>This applies when the mouse pointer is over any
		  part of the board window - the green table or the valid
		  wooden goban. Using the mousewheel won't cause
		  accidental clicks on the goban. So this is a slight
		  difference to the mousebutton navigation.</para>
		</tip>
	  </section>
	</section>

<!-- Section Keyboard control -->
	<section>
	  <title>Keyboard control</title>

	  <para>q5go offers easy keyboard control to navigate through
	  a game tree. Most menu items have a keyboard shortcut, as
	  stated in the menu. The cursor keys offer the basic
	  navigation: left and right move backwards and forwards
	  through the game, while up and down can be used to switch
	  between variations if they are present.</para>

	  <para>Some additional functionality is available through keys
	  not mentioned in the menus:</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <keycap>Escape</keycap>

		  - Forces the window focus back to the board from the
		  comment edit widget.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
			<keycap>Shift</keycap>

			<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem>
				<para>When in normal mode, holding down the shift
				key and
				<emphasis>left</emphasis>

				clicking moves to the
				<emphasis>first</emphasis>

				position of the
				<emphasis>main variation branch</emphasis>

				where the stone at this spot was played.</para>
			  </listitem>

			  <listitem>
				<para>When in normal mode, holding down the shift
				key and
				<emphasis>right</emphasis>

				clicking moves to the
				<emphasis>next</emphasis>

				position within the
				<emphasis>current branch</emphasis>

				where the stone at this spot was played.</para>
			  </listitem>

			  <listitem>
				<para>When the letter mark tool is selected,
				shift-click allows to customize the mark
				text.</para>
			  </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		  </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		  <para>
			<keycap>Control</keycap>
		  </para>

		  <para>In normal mode, to lookup all game positions of a
		  spot, hold down the control key and left-click to find
		  all moves at the given position. The search result will
		  be displayed in a bookmark-like dialog. The lookup is
		  performed in all variations after the current
		  move.</para>

		  <para>The difference to the shift key is, that this
		  lookup searched through all following variations, while
		  the shift key search only checks the main branch. Also,
		  the shift key search finds the first position in the
		  whole game, while the control key search looks up all
		  moves, but only those after the current.</para>
		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</section>
  </chapter>
</book>


